Guide to the Grace Schulman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Grace Schulman papers
1948-2007
YCAL MSS 601
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
18.84
(34 boxes)
This collection consists of material created and accumulated by Grace Schulman during her career as a poet, editor, and educator. Material includes writings, personal papers, correspondence, photographs, audiovisual material, and printed material, documenting the creation of several of Schulman's published volumes of poetry and her edition of The Poems of Marianne Moore (2003), as well as individual poems she published in numerous magazines.
Schulman, Grace
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Grace Schulman on the Sinclair Lewis Fund and the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial Fund, 2002, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 11-12, 23 (audiovisual material): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Grace Schulman
Grace Schulman, American poet and educator, was born in New York City in 1935. She studied at Bard College and graduated from American University in 1955, and received a Ph.D. from New York University in 1971. She is the Distinguished Professor of English at Baruch College, CUNY. She has taught poetry writing at Princeton University, Columbia University, Wesleyan University, Bennington College, and Warren Wilson College. Her work has appeared in the New Yorker, the New Republic, Paris Review, Antaeus, Grand Street, the Yale Review, the Hudson Review, and the Kenyon Review. She served as Poetry Editor of the Nation from 1972 to 2006, and director of the Poetry Center, 92nd Street Y, from 1973 to 1985. Her volumes of poetry include Burn Down the Icons (1976), Hemispheres (1984), For That Day Only (1994), The Paintings of Our Lives (2001), and Days of Wonder: New and Selected Poems (2002). Other works include her edition of The Poems of Marianne Moore (2003), several works of criticism, and translations of the poetry of T. Carmi and Pablo Antonio Cuadra.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of material created and accumulated by Grace Schulman during her career as a poet, editor, and educator. Material includes writings, personal papers, correspondence, photographs, audiovisual material, and printed material, documenting the creation of several of Schulman's published volumes of poetry and her edition of The Poetry of Marianne Moore, as well as individual poems she published in numerous magazines.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: I. June and July 2002 Acquisitions. II. September 2006 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time.
Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. For instance, correspondence and writings can be found in both groupings. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiocassettes; Audiovisual materials; Photographic prints; Videocassettes; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Schulman, Grace
- June and July 2002 Acquisitions, 1; 15.84; (31 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This group contains writings, correspondence, photographs, printed material, audiotapes, videotapes, record albums, personal papers including a scapbook and journals, and correspondence by or relating to Grace Schulman.
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subgroups: Writings and Other Papers; and Correspondence.
  General note
  Formerly classed as Uncat MSS 310.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 11-12 and 23 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Writings and Other Papers
    - Days of Wonder, typescripts with corrections, 3 (Box 1)
    - The Paintings of Our Lives, manuscript, typescripts, and galley proof, 4 (Box 2)
    - Translations of my poems (Box 3)
    - Princeton - ADs (Box 3)
    - Hemispheres (Box 3)
    - Burn Down the Icons, 3 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Days of Wonder, galley proof, 2 (Box 3)
    - Proofs and unfinished mag. versions (Box 3)
    - Houghton Mifflin company (Box 3)
    - Days of Wonder, page proofs, 3 (Box 3)
    - Books - For That Day Only (Box 3)
    - Houghton - paintings, lives (Box 3)
    - Paintings (Box 3)
    - The Best of the Best of American Poetry: 1988-1997 (Box 3)
    - For that Day Only (Box 3)
    - The Painting of Our Lives (Box 3)
    - Hemispheres (Box 3)
    - Houghton - Days of Wonder, 2 (Box 3)
    - Houghton Mifflin/Paintings/lives (Box 3)
    - Notes (Box 3)
    - New book in progress, January 22 (Box 3)
    - The Paintings of Our Lives, typescript, edited, 4 (Box 4)
    - Address book, 3 (Box 5)
    - Letters, "Unterberg poetry center," poets and artists (Box 5)
    - Notebooks, 7 (Box 6)
    - Letters, clippings (Box 7)
    - Bird - CUNY grad. (Box 7)
    - Pen translation (Box 7)
    - Talks (Box 7)
    - Grace and Jerome Schulman - Science 51-poetry (Box 7)
    - Translations - Spanish (Box 7)
    - Readings, 3 (Box 7)
    - "Silhouette" (Box 7)
    - "Mademoiselle," 1953 July, 1959 May; "Poetry" 1964; "Pregled" 1960 (Box 7)
    - "Glamour," "Mademoiselle" (Box 7)
    - "Poetry"; letters; "Elizabeth Kray: a romance", 1964 (Box 7)
    - "Farewell gala performance", 1966 April 16 (Box 7)
    - "Bird," WWC (Box 7)
    - Two poems (Box 7)
    - Poems selected for Grace Schulman (Box 7)
    - The Nation (Box 7)
    - Howe (Box 7)
    - Cuadra (Box 7)
    - "Mademoiselle: college number", 1952 August (Box 7)
    - Notes (Box 8)
    - Awards (Box 8)
    - My translations (Hebrew, Spanish) (Box 8)
    - Poems (Box 8)
    - Poetry worksheets (Box 8)
    - Prose MS (Box 8)
    - Irving Howe (Box 8)
    - Clippings (Box 8)
    - Term papers, 2 (Box 9)
    - NYU commencement program (Box 9)
    - Misc. poems (Box 9)
    - Poems by GS, "Ms.", 1977 (Box 9)
    - "The poetry center" (Box 9)
    - Letters from GS, 2000-2001 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence (Box 9)
    - Misc. papers, poems, etc. (Box 9)
    - "The national book award," clippings, etc. (Box 9)
    - Center for Inter-American relations (Box 9)
    - "The 71st annual awards of the poetry center" (Box 9)
    - Miscellanea, 2 (Box 9)
    - Clippings (Box 9)
    - Poetry center brochures, 1974-1980 (Box 9)
    - "The poetry center", 3 (Box 9)
    - The Nation (Box 9)
    - Negatives (Box 10)
    - Slides (Box 10)
    - Wedding photos, 2 (Box 10)
    - Metal Stamp Schulmann's address (Box 10)
    - Audiocassettes, 12 (Box 11)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Grace Schulman: reading, 1984 April; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613436)
      - New Letters on the Air, a production of New Letters magazine, University of Missouri, K.C., 1984 July; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613444)
      - Grace Schulman and Terry Gross on Fresh Air, WUHY-FM Philadelphia, 1981 December 9; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613451)
      - Grace Schulman - poetry reading, University of Montana, Missoula, 1980 January 31; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613469)
        A list of contents is included with this audiocassette.
        Poetry Editor
        The Examination
        Burn Down Icons
        Letter to Helen
        Birds Blighted Tree
        Stars & Moon
        Blessed is Light
        Easy as Wind
        Sutton
        Letter Nicaragua
        Hammond Map Store
        The Swans
        Villanelle
        Metamorphosis
        Horses on Grass
        Song of Ourselves
        The Flight
      - Grace Schulman - poetry reading, University of Montana, Missoula, 1980 January 31; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613477)
        This audiocassette appears to be a duplicate.
      - Women's Studies, Women as Literary Innovators, lecturer: Grace Schulman, 1976; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613485)
      - Grace Schulman, undated; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613493)
      - Blair Brown; Grace Schulman, undated; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613501)
      - Grace Schulman/David Ignatow, Buttenwieser Hall, 1982 May 3; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613519)
      - Grace Schulman/Berghash, WBAI-FM, 1986 April 11; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613527)
      - Metamorphosis, Glenn Lieberman, 1981; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613535)
      - PEN Writers, Censorship Project, undated; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002104613543)
    - Videocassettes
      - San Miguel Poetry Week, Naomi Shihab Nye/Grace Schulman, 1999; YCALMSS601_0001; 1; 01:33:01 (Box 12, Item barcode 39002102300119)
      - Grace, undated; YCALMSS601_0002; 1; 00:26:23 (Box 12, Item barcode 39002102300127)
        The video appears to be a series of home videos. It begins with black and white footage of a baby. Most of the footage on the tape is black and white although a few segments are in color.
    - Days of Wonder, 2 (Box 13)
    - "Where we stand: women poets on literary tradition," clippings (Box 13)
    - Shahid (Box 13)
    - "Burn down the icons" (Box 13)
    - Houghton (Box 13)
    - Letters, 2 (Box 13)
    - Versions (Box 13)
    - Letters and poem (Box 13)
    - Party readings, 2002 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence (Box 14)
    - Kauffer (Box 14)
    - ML Rosenthal (Box 14)
    - Reviews (Box 14)
    - Sketches of David ...? by his wife (Box 14)
    - Holocaust Mom (GS notes) (Box 14)
    - Empty notebook (Box 14)
    - Poems by Agha Shahid Ali (Box 14)
    - Letters, "American poet", 1998-1999 (Box 14)
    - Poems by Erica Jong, etc (Box 14)
    - Interview with me by David Avidar (Box 14)
    - Letters (Box 14)
    - Photos, Scrapbook, 2 (Box 15)
    - Poems (Box 15)
    - Photos (Box 15)
    - Poems (Box 15)
    - "Lights, camera, poetry!" (Box 15)
    - "To Stanley Kunitz, with love" (Box 15)
    - "Poets of Nicaragua" (Box 15)
    - The Hudson Review, 1976-1978; 2 (Box 15)
    - "Congressional dictionary", 1953 (Box 15)
    - "Antaeus: poetry and poetics" 30-31 (Box 15)
    - The Yale Review, 1997 (Box 15)
    - "Parnasus", 1978 (Box 15)
    - "Poetry", 1976, 1981, 1987; 3 (Box 15)
    - The Hudson Review, 1974, 1976; 2 (Box 15)
    - The Hudson Review, 1974, 1979,1987; 5 (Box 16)
    - Offprint of poems by Pablo Antonio (Box 16)
    - "Review", 1974 (Box 16)
    - The Kenyon Review, 1994; 3 (Box 16)
    - Ms., 1973; 2 (Box 16)
    - The New Orleans Review, 1969 (Box 16)
    - Photos (Box 16)
    - Journal, 2 (Box 17)
    - Notebook (Box 17)
    - "The mind is an enchanting thing," "The Cloisters" (Box 17)
    - Early notes (Box 17)
    - Notes (computer) (Box 17)
    - Letter to GS (Box 17)
    - My first visit to Yaddo, 1973 (Box 17)
    - Poem by GS (Box 17)
    - Poems by GS, 1981 (Box 17)
    - Cash book (Box 17)
    - Notes by GS (Box 17)
    - Diary, 1988-1992 (Box 17)
    - Notebook (Box 17)
    - Diary, 7 (Box 17)
    - Marianne Moore, The Poetry of Engagement, 2 (Box 18)
    - "Blue in Green" (Box 18)
    - The Poems of Marianne Moore, 2 (Box 18)
    - "Sensitive" (Box 18)
    - The American Jewish Committee award (Box 19 (Oversize))
    - Broadsides and other printed ephemera, 2 (Box 20 (Oversize))
    - Posters (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Burn down the icons - reviews (Box 22 (Oversize))
    - Covers of the books The Days of Wonder and The Paintings of Our Lives (Box 22 (Oversize))
    - "Treasury of American Jewish Poets" phonographic records, 2 (Box 23 (Record album storage))
    - Mother's scrapbook (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Correspondence
    - Unsorted correspondence, 22 (Box 25)
      Includes letters from E. McKnight Kaufer, Marianne Moore, and Bernard Waldman. Also includes newspaper clippings and Bernard Waldman's immigration certificate.
    - Introduction to the readings by GS (Box 26)
    - Unsorted correspondence (Box 26)
    - First Magazine acceptance letters, 1968 (Box 26)
    - Editors, 1980-1997; 4 (Box 26)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 1970s; 2 (Box 26)
    - Amichai, Yehuda (Box 26)
    - Bell, Marvin (Box 26)
    - Berg, Steve (Box 26)
    - Blumenthal, Michael (Box 26)
    - Corn, Alfred (Box 26)
    - Eberhard, Richard and Erica Jong (Box 26)
    - Hackes, Marvin (Box 26)
    - Hamell, Sam (Box 26)
    - Hirsch, Edward (Box 26)
    - Howard, Richard (Box 26)
    - Ignatow, David (Box 26)
    - Jacobson, Josephine (Box 26)
    - McClatchy, J. D. (Box 26)
    - Kaufmann, Shirley (Box 26)
    - Kirchwey, Karl (Box 26)
    - Merwin, W. S. (Box 26)
    - Swenson/Knudson (Box 26)
    - Moore, [Marianne?] (Box 26)
    - Ozick, Cynthia (Box 26)
    - Rendall, Ann (Box 26)
    - Rosenthal, M. L. (Box 26)
    - Trask, Willard (Box 26)
    - Weiss, T. and R. Weiss (Box 26)
    - Yates, Dick (Box 26)
    - Waldman, Marcella [GS's mother], 5 (Box 26)
    - Waldman, Marcella and Walter (Box 27)
    - Family tree (Box 27)
    - Mom archive (Box 27)
    - GS's letter to Marcella Waldman (Box 27)
    - Painting, letters to editors (Box 27)
    - Uncle Josh (Box 27)
    - Beta and Helen (Box 27)
    - Father, uncle Josh and aunt Beta (Box 27)
    - Grandfather Dave (Box 27)
    - About GS (Box 27)
    - Ashley Montagne (Box 27)
    - Correspondence - mom (Box 27)
    - Jerome Schulman (husband) (Box 27)
    - Baruch College (Box 27)
    - Condolence - mom (Box 27)
    - Postcards received (Box 27)
    - Correspondence, 1990s-2001; 2 (Box 28)
    - 92nd Street Y, Poetry center uproar, 2 (Box 28)
    - The Nation, 1970s; 2 (Box 28)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 1970s; 2 (Box 28)
    - Y discovery nation (Box 28)
    - The Nation, 3 (Box 29)
    - Projects and papers by GS (Box 30)
    - Address book - G and Jerome Shulman (Box 30)
    - The Poetry of Solitude (Box 30)
    - "The Haunted" (Box 30)
    - Photo album [empty], newspapers (Box 30)
    - Clippings and poems by GS, 3 (Box 30)
    - National Book Awards, 1998 (Box 30)
    - Correspondence: Yadoo-Venice (Box 30)
    - Correspondence, etc. (Box 30)
    - Correspondence editors, 1990s (Box 30)
    - Brandeis, National Book Awards, other juries (Box 30)
    - Poems (Box 30)
    - Moore (Box 30)
    - Programs, invitations (Box 30)
    - Teaching - Baruch (Box 30)
    - 92nd Street Y, Tisch Center for the Arts (Box 31)
    - The Nation (Box 31)
    - Published poems (Box 31)
    - Poems published in The Nation, 2 (Box 31)
    - NYR The Nation clippings (Box 31)
- September 2006 Acquisition, 2; 3; (3 boxes)
  This group contains orrespondence, writings and related papers.
  Organized into two subgroups: Writings and Other Papers.
  Formerly classed as Uncat MSS 896
  - Writings
    - Paintings of Our Lives, 2001; 5 (Box 32)
    - Days of Wonder, 2001; 10 (Box 32)
    - Poems of Marianne Moore, 2003; 2 (Box 32)
    - Poems of Marianne Moore, 2003; 18 (Box 33)
    - Poems of Marianne Moore, 2003; 6 (Box 34)
    - Broken String, circa 2007; 4 (Box 34)
  - Other Papers
    - Recent Awards, 2 (Box 34)
    - The Nation (Box 34)
    - Yezzi Merwin, 3 (Box 34)
    - Correspondence (Box 34)
    - Editors, 2 (Box 34)